<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The complaint of M. Tenter-hooke the proiector, and Sir Thomas Dodger the patentee.</title>
            <author>Taylor, John, 1580-1653.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1641</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 7 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 1 1-bit group-IV TIFF page image.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B06331</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T443</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Interim Tract Supplement Guide C.20.f.2[12]</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99886857</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">ocm99886857</idno>
            <idno type="VID">181343</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B06331)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 181343)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books; Tract supplement ; A1:1[12])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The complaint of M. Tenter-hooke the proiector, and Sir Thomas Dodger the patentee.</title>
                  <author>Taylor, John, 1580-1653.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 sheet ([1] p.) : ill. (woodcuts).  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by  E[lizabeth]. P[urslowe]. for Francis Coles, dwelling in the Old Baily,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1641.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signed at end John Taylor.</note>
                  <note>In two columns with a woodcut over both columns.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from Wing CD-ROM, 1996.</note>
                  <note>Verse: "If any aske, what things these monsters be,".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Political poetry, English --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-01</date>
            <label>Emma (Leeson) Huber</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Rekeyed and resubmitted</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:181343:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 1 -->
            <head>The complaint of M. Tenter-hooke the <hi>Proiector,</hi> and Sir Thomas Dodger the <hi>Patentee</hi>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>depiction of a rat dressed as a man presenting money bags to a patentee</figDesc>
                  <p>I have brought money to fill your Cheſt,
For which I am curſt by moſt and leaſt</p>
                  <p>Ov'r many yeares ſcraping is left at a clap,
All thou haſt gotten by others miſhap,</p>
               </figure>
            </head>
            <argument>
               <lg>
                  <l>If any aske, what things theſe <hi>Monſters</hi> be,</l>
                  <l>Tis a <hi>Projector,</hi> and a <hi>Patentee:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Such, as like <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ermine or'e this Land did crawle,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And grew ſo rich, they gaind the Devill and all.</l>
               </lg>
            </argument>
            <lg>
               <l>LOe I, that lately was a <hi>Man</hi> of faſhion,</l>
               <l>The <hi>Bug-beare</hi> and the <hi>Scarcrow</hi> of this Nation,</l>
               <l>Th'admired mighty <hi>Mounte-banke</hi> of <hi>Fame,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>The Juggling <hi>Hocus Pocus</hi> of good name,</l>
               <l>The <hi>Bull-begger,</hi> who did affright and feare,</l>
               <l>And rake, and pull, teare, pill, pole, ſhave, and ſheare,</l>
               <l>Now <hi>Time</hi> hath pluck'd the <hi>Vizard</hi> from my face,</l>
               <l>I am the onely Image of diſgrace.</l>
               <l>My ugly ſhape I hid ſo cunningly</l>
               <l>(Cloſe cover'd with the cloake of honeſty)</l>
               <l>That from the <hi>Eaſt</hi> to <hi>VVeſt,</hi> from <hi>South</hi> to <hi>North,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>I was a man eſteem'd of ex'lent worth.</l>
               <l>And (ſweet Sir <hi>Thomas Dodger</hi>) for your ſake,</l>
               <l>My ſtudious time I ſpent, my ſleepes I brake,</l>
               <l>My braines I toſt, with many a ſtrange vagary,</l>
               <l>And (like a Spanniell) did both fetch and carry,</l>
               <l>To you, ſuch <hi>Projects,</hi> as I could invent,</l>
               <l>Not thinking there would come a Parliament.</l>
               <l>I was the Great <hi>Projector,</hi> and from me,</l>
               <l>Your worſhip learn'd to be a <hi>Patentee,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>I had the Art to cheat the Common-weale,</l>
               <l>And you had tricks and ſlights to paſſe the Seale.</l>
               <l>I tooke the paines, I travell'd, ſearch'd, and ſought,</l>
               <l>Which (by your power) were into Patents wrought.</l>
               <l>What was I but your journey-man, I pray,</l>
               <l>To bring your worke to you, both night and day:</l>
               <l>I found <hi>Stuffe,</hi> and you brought it ſo about</l>
               <l>You (like a skilfull <hi>Taylor</hi>) cut it out,</l>
               <l>And faſhion'd it, but now (to our diſpleaſure)</l>
               <l>You fail'd exceedingly, in taking meaſure.</l>
               <l>My legs were Screwes, to raiſe thee high or low,</l>
               <l>According as your power did <hi>Ebbe</hi> or <hi>Flow:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And at your will I was Screwd up too high</l>
               <l>That tott'ring, I have broke my necke thereby.</l>
               <l>For you, I made my <hi>Fingers fiſh-hookes</hi> ſtill</l>
               <l>To catch at all <hi>Trades,</hi> either good or ill,</l>
               <l>I car'd not much who loſt, ſo we might get,</l>
               <l>For all was <hi>Fiſh</hi> that came into the <hi>Net.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>For you (as in my Picture plaine appeares)</l>
               <l>I put a <hi>Swines face</hi> on, an <hi>Aſses eares,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>The one to liſten unto all I heard</l>
               <l>Wherein your worſhips profit was prefer'd.</l>
               <l>The other to taſt all things, good or bad</l>
               <l>(As Hogs will doe) where profit may be had,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Grape, Starch, Tobacco, Pipes, Pins, Butter, Haye,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Wine, Coales, Cards, Dice,</hi> and all came in my way.</l>
               <l>I brought your worſhip, every day and houre,</l>
               <l>And hope to be defended by your power,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>
                  <hi>Sir</hi> Thomas Dodgers Anſwer!</head>
               <l>ALas good <hi>Tenter-hooke,</hi> I tell thee plaine,</l>
               <l>To ſeeke for helpe of me tis but in vaine:</l>
               <l>My <hi>Patent,</hi> which I ſtood upon of late,</l>
               <l>Is like an <hi>Almanacke</hi> that's out of <hi>Date.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>T'had force and vertue once, ſtrange things to doe,</l>
               <l>But now it wants both force and vertue too:</l>
               <l>his was the turne of whirling <hi>Fortunes</hi> wheele,</l>
               <l>When we leaſt dream'd we ſhould her changing feele.</l>
               <l>Then <hi>Time,</hi> and fortune, both with joynt conſent</l>
               <l>Brought us to ruine by a Parliament:</l>
               <l>I doe confeſſe thou broughtſt me ſweet conceits</l>
               <l>Which now I find were but alluring baits,</l>
               <l>And I (to much an Aſſe) did lend my eare,</l>
               <l>To credit all thou ſaydſt, as well as heare.</l>
               <l>Thou in the <hi>Project</hi> of the <hi>Soape</hi> didſt toyle,</l>
               <l>But 'twas ſo ſlippery, and too full of oyle,</l>
               <l>That people wondred how we held it faſt,</l>
               <l>But now it is quite ſlipp'd from us at laſt.</l>
               <l>The <hi>Project</hi> for the <hi>Starch</hi> thy wit found out,</l>
               <l>Twas ſtiffe a while, now limber as a Clout,</l>
               <l>The Pagan weed <hi>(Tobacco)</hi> was our hope</l>
               <l>In <hi>Leafe, Pricke, Role, Ball, Pudding, Pipe,</hi> or <hi>Rope.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Braſseele, Varina, Meavis, Trinidado,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Saint <hi>Chriſtophers, Virginia,</hi> or <hi>Barvado;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Bermudas, Providentia, Shallowcongo,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And the moſt part of all the reſt (<hi>Mundungo</hi>)</l>
               <l>That Patent, with a whiffe is ſpent and broke,</l>
               <l>And all our hopes (in fumo) turn'd to ſmoake.</l>
               <l>Thou framdſt the <hi>Butter</hi> Patent in thy braines,</l>
               <l>(A rope and butter take thee for thy paines)</l>
               <l>I had forgot <hi>Tobacco-pipes,</hi> which are</l>
               <l>Now like to thou and I, but brittle ware.</l>
               <l>Dice run againſt us, we at <hi>Cards</hi> are croſt,</l>
               <l>We both are turn'd up <hi>Noddies,</hi> and all's loſt.</l>
               <l>Thus from-<hi>Sice-ſinke,</hi> we'r ſunke below <hi>Dewee-ace,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And both of us are Impes of blacke diſgrace.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Pins</hi> pricke us, and <hi>Wine</hi> frets our very hearts,</l>
               <l>That we have rais'd the price of <hi>Pints</hi> and <hi>Quarts.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Thou (in mine eares) thy lyes and tales didſt foyſt.</l>
               <l>And madſt me up the price of <hi>Sea-coales</hi> hoyſt.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Corne, Leather, Partrich, Pheaſant, Rags, Gold twist,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Thou brought'ſt all to my <hi>Mill,</hi> what was't we miſt?</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Weights, Bonlace, Mowſtraps, new, new, Corporation,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Rattles, Seadans,</hi> of rare invented faſhions,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Silke, Tallow, Hobby-horſes, wood, red-herring,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Law, Conſcience, Iuſtice, ſwearing,</hi> and For-ſwearing.</l>
               <l>All theſe thou broughtſt to me, and ſtill I thought,</l>
               <l>That every thing was good that profit brought,</l>
               <l>But now all's found to be ill gotten pelfe,</l>
               <l>I'le ſhift for one doe thou ſhift for thy ſelfe.</l>
            </lg>
            <trailer>Finis.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>JOHN TAYLOR London Printed by <hi>H. P.</hi> for <hi>Frances Coles</hi> dwelling in the Old-Baily.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
